<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The seauen spirituall exercises of a deuout soule Containing the life and death of our sauiour Christ: compiled in seauen meditations, replenished with most godly, and deuout motions, and seruing for the seauen dayes in the weeke.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00337</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115252</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850471</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850471</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00337)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1298:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The seauen spirituall exercises of a deuout soule Containing the life and death of our sauiour Christ: compiled in seauen meditations, replenished with most godly, and deuout motions, and seruing for the seauen dayes in the weeke.</title>
                  <author>Bull, John, fl. 1613, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 114 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Iohn Budge, and are to be solde at the great south-doore of Paules, and at Britaines Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: I.B. = John Bull?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Biography --  Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15678:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15678:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SEAVEN SPIRITVALL Exerciſes of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Soule.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING the Life and Death of our Sauiour CHRIST: compiled in <hi>ſeauen Meditations, repleniſhed</hi> with moſt godly, and deuout <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſeruing for the ſeauen</hi> dayes in the Weeke.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALME 119.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will meditate in thy precepts, and conſider thy wayes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to be ſolde at the great South-doore of Paules, and at Britaines Burſſe. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15678:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15678:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>WORSHIPFVLL,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>William Bull,</hi> MAYOR of the Citie of WELS, I. B. <hi>Wiſheth all proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> in this life, and <hi>eternall happineſſe</hi> in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F all men are by nature and duty bound to gratifie their
<pb facs="tcp:15678:3"/>wel-deſeruing Friends, (moſt deare, and much reſpected VNCLE) then muſt I not ouerſlip time to make requitall of your manifold kindneſſes, by ſome ſlender gift, ſuch as the zeale of my dutie, and the abilitie of my minde is able to performe. And now to make it appeare, not ſo much in comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as in action, I haue ſent you a ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, which (in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome Diuines, whom I reuerence in my heart) is, for matter, of worthy reſpect; for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, plaine; for practiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:15678:3"/>godly; and (I hope) for the fruits of it, profitable: for what of higher re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, of more facilitie, of deeper deuotion, and of greater comfort, then the meditation of the Hiſtorie of our Sauiour CHRIST, which you ſee here parted into ſeauen dayes practiſe, and may be the Chriſtians daily taske. I will ſay no more of it, onely vſe it, peruſe it, practiſe it: and after your charitable cenſure, if it may ſeeme worthy your patronage, claime it as your owne; your owne you may then call
<pb facs="tcp:15678:4"/>it, for without you, it had neuer ſeene the Sunne, nor the Sunne it. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexe of your fauours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, and the vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued kindneſſe of <hi>Some</hi> that are neare allyed to you (whom I onely point at,
<note place="margin">R. B. &amp;c.</note> I neede no more, as alſo the godly diſpoſition of you all in matters of pietie and deuotion) haue called this light out of darkneſſe, and made it (that long hath wandred from the Author) like a wearyed Pilgrime to flye to you for prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>As you loue Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:15678:4"/>ſo fauour it, and as you fauour godlineſſe, ſo loue <hi>It.</hi> Make it your daily,
<note place="margin">Viz. <hi>This Booke.</hi>
               </note> though not your whole, taske: and reſolue of this, that Chriſt cals men, as well to Mount Tabor by diuine Meditation, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his goodneſſe and glory; as <hi>Caeſar</hi> cals them to beare the Sword, for the defence and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of authoritie.</p>
            <p>Thus crauing your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable acceptance of this poore mite, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the patronage of the ſame, I wiſh you all health and happineſſe. Leauing this to you, with
<pb facs="tcp:15678:5"/>the remembrance of my humble dutie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> this 3. of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1612.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Coſen in all ſeruice to be commanded. <hi>I. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:15678:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE to the ſeauen Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, of the Life, <hi>and Death of our</hi> SAVIOVR CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongst all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, (if we may giue credit to an Ancient Writer) there is none more profitable,
<note place="margin">In Prol. of the Medit. of the Life of <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
               </note> then the Meditations of the Life and Death of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. For as they worke in vs, a deſpiſing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb facs="tcp:15678:6"/>of all viſible things; ſo doe they arme vs againſt all the power of the world, the fleſh, and the Diuell: They purchaſe familiaritie with God; they procure his loue towards vs; they make vs confident, and they bring our ſoules to the Paradiſe of all vertues, and height of all heauenly perfections.</p>
            <p>For, where may wee finde the force, vertue, and true effects of pouerti-, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, patience, meekneſſe, loue, obedience, and other celeſliall Graces, more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly diſplayed, then in the life of our Sauiour. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh
<pb facs="tcp:15678:6"/>rightly, when he ſaith: <hi>That man that would get vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe vertue, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in vaine, if hee ſeeke it any where elſe, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it of any other, then of him that is Lord of all vertues, whoſe doctrine is the rule of Wiſedome, whoſe mercy is the work of Iuſtice, whoſe life is the example of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and whoſe death is the perfect preſident of Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Exerciſe this ſweet and holy Teacher ſpent and conſumed his whole time, making bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and fruit of the godly
<pb facs="tcp:15678:7"/>collections, which hee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together of the anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties and bitterneſſe of Chriſt his Paſsion: in whoſe perſon he paſionately ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sup. Can. Serm.</hi> 63.</note> 
               <hi>O homo, vide quae pro te patior, non eſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor ſicut dolor meus.</hi> Whereof alſo he was not at any time vnmindfull, as he witneſſeth of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Therefore a man ſhall doe a worke of exceeding worth, if once (at the leaſt) in euery weeke, eyther by prayer, or Meditation, hee runne ouer the whole life of our <hi>Sauiour Ieſus:</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no prayer more acceptable vnto him, then
<pb facs="tcp:15678:7"/>that, in which is made a remembrance and comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of his life, and death, of his merits, and benefits which hee hath done for vs.</p>
            <p>And that this may be done more fitly, the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> hath comprehended the Life, Death, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt, in ſeauen Prayers or Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions following, that they might ſerue for the ſeauen dayes in the weeke; and the ſame in manner of a thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, ſeeing there is no benefit for which wee owe greater thanks vnto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God. Then let God
<pb facs="tcp:15678:8"/>haue the glory, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires no more of vs, then the Confeſsion and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his benefits, <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima beneficiorum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos eſt ipſa memoria be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom</hi> 25. <hi>ſup. Mat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; perpetua confeſſio gratiarum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome;</hi> The beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of the graces of God is the mention and confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his graces.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15678:8"/>
            <head>SEAVEN MEDITATIONS, of the Life of IESVS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="meditation">
               <head>MEDITAT. I.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Christ deſcendeth from heauen, and is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Virgines Wombe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Render vnto thee immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall thanks (oh ſweet Ieſu) that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15678:9"/>for the loue of mee, didſt deſcend from thy Regall Pallace, and high boſome of thy Father, into this low vaile of all miſeries, and vouchſafedſt to take vpon thee humane fleſh, in the holy wombe of thy bleſſed Mother,
<note place="margin">Mat. 1.18.</note> I beſeech thee (O Lord) to prepare my heart a Tabernacle for thee, and to that end to adorne the ſame with all manner of vertues, that thou maiſt therein make perpetuall habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Oh would to God it might pleaſe thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to make my heart
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15678:9"/>to be ſuch towards thee, that I be not afraid to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite thee, but that thou maiſt come to dwell in mee, and that I may be fit to receiue thee with ſpirituall delight,
<note place="margin">Luke 19.6</note> as <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> which receiued thee ioyfully: and that thou maiſt ſweetly reſt in my heart without end. Oh that I could embrace thee with the armes of ſtrong affection, that at any time, I be not drawne from thee by thought, word, deed, or vaine ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15678:10"/>
                  <head>Mary <hi>viſiteth</hi> Elizabeth.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet Ieſu) for that after thou wert conceiued in the wombe of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> thou wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledſt her, by thy Angell <hi>Gabriel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 1.39</note> to goe by the Mountaines and viſit <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> that ſhe might ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and congratulate with her, for that GOD had made her barren wombe to beare. Thou didſt not diſdaine to be ſhut nine Moneths in the glorious bowels of thy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15678:10"/>Mother. Therefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to giue me the grace of true Humilitie, and ſo to imprint the ſame in my heart, that thou maiſt alwayes finde me ready in thoſe things that appertaine vnto the godly worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of thee.</p>
                  <p>Grant (O Lord) that my heart may ſtill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine all worldly things, and that I may continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſire to reſt and dwell in thee, and that my heart may be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to endure any low eſtate for thee, that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly enduredſt the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15678:11"/>degree of humilitie for my ſake.
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.7.8</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Christ is borne.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thanks (O my ſweet Ieſus) which art borne of the moſt holy Virgine, without damage of Virgines puritie, and who laid thee ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, being borne, in a Manger or Cribbe, as poore and mortall; and humbly worſhipped thee as immortall God,
<note place="margin">Luke 1.46</note> and Creator of all things. I pray thy diuine mercy, that thou wouldeſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15678:11"/>to be continually borne in mee by a new deſire of Charitie, and that thou alone maiſt be my whole deſire, my one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulnes, and firme hope of my heart. Let it be pleaſing vnto thee, that I alwayes ſeeke thee, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes thinke on thee, and alwayes feruently loue thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15678:12"/>
                  <head>Christ is wrapped in baſe clothing.</head>
                  <p>I Giue vnto thee infinite thankes (O ſweet Ieſu) that being borne, waſt ſubiect to the bitterneſſe of the ayre and cold ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and yet createdſt the ayre, and ordereſt the ſeaſons: thou didſt not diſdaine to be wrapped in baſe clothing, and to partake of my weakeneſſe and miſerie, to ſucke vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines Milke from the breſt of thy glorious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the innocent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15678:12"/>Lambe of God, in the forme of a poore and ſimple Babe; when thou waſt indeed the true om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God. Thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cameſt poore for our ſakes, that art indeed the King of heauen and earth, that we through thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.9</note> might be made rich.</p>
                  <p>Grant then (O Lord) that in thy ſight, I may alwayes be a true Infant in Humilitie, thy Childe in Innocencie; and that I may be alwayes truely poore in ſpirit, but rich in grace, and plentifull in goodneſſe. Grant that for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15678:13"/>the loue of thee, I refuſe nothing in this World, that is eyther bitter, or laborious; that I loue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world, but thee; deſire to poſſeſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing aboue thee; nor eſteem any worldly thing in compariſon of thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Chriſt is worſhipped of the Shepheards.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O bountifull Ieſu) that as ſoone as thou waſt borne, was celebrated with the ſweet Hymnes of holy Angels,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.14</note> and worſhipped
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15678:13"/>of the Shepheards,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.20</note> with great ioy and admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whom thou diddeſt chooſe to publiſh thy praiſe, <hi>non ſapientes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Beda.</note> 
                     <hi>ſed ſimplices, qui fucare audita neſcirent;</hi> not the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the world, but plaine and ſimple men, that knew to publiſh no more then they heard.</p>
                  <p>Giue mee grace (O Lord) to perſeuere al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in thy praiſe with gladnes, that I may ſeeke therein the ſocietie of the godly, and in ſeeking may finde thee; and (found) may ioy in thee; and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, may enioy thee eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15678:14"/>Finally, that my ioy may burſt forth with them, to publiſh abroad theſe glad tidings to the comfort of others, as they haue comforted me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Christ is Circumciſed, and called <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BE euer praiſed and glorified (O ſweet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu) for that the eight day (according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of other Infants) thou wouldeſt be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.21.</note> and diddeſt begin to ſhed thy bloud for the loue of mee, in thy moſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15678:14"/>tender age, and that thou wouldſt comſort me with ineffable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation, wert called <hi>Ieſus,</hi> a Sauiour;
<note place="margin">Mat. 1.21.</note> to ſaue mee, that otherwiſe had vtterly periſhed.</p>
                  <p>I beſeech thee (O Lord) to account mee in the number of thy elect, and to write my name in the booke of the bleſſed. And that thou wouldeſt circumciſe my hart from all ſuperfluitie, that is, from idle and hurtfull ſpeeches, from vniuſt workes, and from impure and vaine thoughts, and cogitations. Set a watch before mine eyes, keepe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15678:15"/>the dore of my lips, and ſo ſearch my heart, that I may confine my ſelfe within the bounds of thy will. Oh my Redeemer, thou art called <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that is, a <hi>Sauiour:</hi> for to thee onely it belongeth to giue ſaluation. Therfore I pray thee (O Lord) that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of this ſweet Name of <hi>Sauiour,</hi> may expell from mee all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, al inordinate faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, and ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; that it may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due mee with a ſtedfaſt hope of thy mercy, and may ſaue mee from all the power of ſin, the rage
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15678:15"/>of Sathan, and the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full delights of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Chriſt is worſhipped of the Wiſe men.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet Ieſu) that wert found of the <hi>Magi,</hi> or wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſeeking thee with ſincere faith, and inward deuotion, by the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a Starre; who fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe vpon their knees before thee, offered Gold, Frankencenſe, and Mirrhe.</p>
                  <p>Grant (O Lord) that I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15678:16"/>may ſeeke thee in the companie and ſocietie of thoſe Wiſe-men, not in Bethlehem, but euen in the center of my heart, and (being found in the ſame) I may worſhip thee in ſpirit and in truth, that I may offer vnto thee, the Gold of pure Charitie,
<note place="margin">Gregor. in Homil.</note> the Incenſe of true Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Mirrhe of perfect Mortification: fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, grant me grace, that with readineſſe of heart, and willingneſſe of minde, I may beſtow all my ſtrength, and power in the imitation and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of thy moſt holy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15678:16"/>life. And if at any time I erre from thy truth, make (O Lord) thy Word to be the ſtarre of my guide to leade mee till I finde thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is preſented in the Temple.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O Lord Ieſus Chriſt) for that thou (to leaue vs the example of Obedience and Humilitie) wouldeſt be ſubiect to the Law for the loue of vs,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.22.</note> for that thou wouldeſt be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Temple in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15678:17"/>Armes of thy bleſſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and wouldeſt the Oblation of two Turtle Doues (not of him that was rich,
<note place="margin">Leu. 12.6.</note> but of a poore man) to be offered for thee.
<note place="margin">Luke 2.25.38.</note> When <hi>Simeon</hi> with <hi>Anna</hi> the Propheteſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing at thy preſence, did giue a worthy teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of thy glory.</p>
                  <p>Grant that it may pleaſe thee (O Lord) not to ſuffer the leaſt thought or imagination of vanitie at any time hereafter, to enter into my heart, and more eſpecially, that I be not lifted vp with pride, nor carryed with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15678:17"/>preſumption. O how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py were I if all manner of preſumption, were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht from mee, and all deſire of worldly fauours, together with the inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate conceit of Selfe-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, were extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in mee?</p>
                  <p>Grant to me thy grace (O Lord) that I may be careleſſe of vaine oftenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that I ſubmit my ſelfe to all men, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly obey them for thy ordinance ſake. And as thou (O Lord) cameſt not to deſtroy, but to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the Law, ſo direct and ſanctifie my heart, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15678:18"/>helpe me with thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, that I may be obedient to thy Law, and performe thoſe duties in thy ſight, as may pleaſe thee, and ſtand for thy glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus flyeth into Egipt.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet Ieſus) for that euen in thy minoritie thou diddeſt beginne to ſuffer perſecution, and diſdainedſt not to flie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Egypt, to auoide the bloudy hands of <hi>Herod,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 2.13.</note> thogh thou mightſt haue
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15678:18"/>cruſht him with thy Rod of Iron, and daſht him in pieces like a Potters veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</p>
                  <p>Grant mee grace that in all my perſecutions, tribulations and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I may wholy flye vnto thee, as my onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge; onely ſeeke thee, as my chiefe treaſure; and call vpon thee, as the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hope of my ſaluation. And how often ſoeuer thou impoſeſt any of thoſe croſſes vpon mee, grant that I may endure them with all patience; abide them with all tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſuffer them with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15678:19"/>all gladnes of hart, giuing thee continuall thankes, for all things that may pleaſe thee to appoint to happen vnto mee: and in euery eſtate to learn me to be content: Laſtly, guide mee with thy free Spirit, that at the ſummons of thy Angels, or at the voyce of thy word in the mouth of thy Miniſters, I may be ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to riſe from the bloody purſuit of Sinne and Sathan, that ſeeke to deſtroy my ſoule.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15678:19"/>
                  <head>Ieſus ſitteth among the Doctors.</head>
                  <p>I Likewiſe giue thankes to thee (o Lord Ieſus) for that thy Mother ſought thee with great ſorrow, when thou remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt in the Temple, and after three dayes found thee with great ioy, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the middeſt of the Doctors,
<note place="margin">Luk. 2.46.</note> whom thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt heare, and diſputedſt with them, aſtoniſhing their harts with thy great Wiſedome, which they could not in any wiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15678:20"/>O Lord, for thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, grant mee, that I be neuer ſeperated from thee, nor thou from me: Put from mee all ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and feare: expell the coldneſſe of affection from my heart, which is ſo much diſpleaſing vnto thee; and giue me a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect deuotion, and an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent thirſt after thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which may ſo poſſeſſe my Soule, that I neuer grow faint, or wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in ſeruing thee. And if at any time I finde not the comfort of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; ſo touch my heart (ô Lord) with an ardent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15678:20"/>deſire of thee, that I neuer ceaſe till I haue found the comfort of thy preſence againe, and may ioyfully ſay with thy Spouſe;
<note place="margin">Cant. 3.4</note> 
                     <hi>I haue found him whom my Soule loued.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="meditation">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15678:21"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. 2.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is Baptized.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Giue THEE thanks (ô moſt ſweet IESVS) for that thou wouldeſt be baptized, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Riuer Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, by the hands of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.15.</note> thy Seruant, and fore-runner, to fulfill all righteouſneſſe. Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe (ô Lord) to purge mee in this life, and to make me cleane from all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15678:21"/>my ſinnes: Confirme in me this thy Couenant of grace, and ſeale vnto me the aſſurance of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes and waſhing away of my ſins by thy bloud. Let mee ſurfet with the loue of thee, and with the vehement deſire of thy heauenly kingdome. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion me (ô Lord) to thine owne will and pleaſure, before my Soule depart from the impriſonment of my body, that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not to diſpute with thee, but willingly to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelfe to thy holy ordinance: That leauing this pilgrimage, I may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15678:22"/>forth-with be with thee, that I may alwayes ſee thee, and alwayes enioy the happy eternity, which hath no end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is tempted of Sathan in the Deſart.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O bountifull Ieſu) that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Deſart, diddeſt faſt fortie dayes and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie nights, and afterwards ſufferedſt thy ſelfe to be tempted of Sathan,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.2.3</note> and when he was ouer-come, the Angels came, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred vnto thee.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15678:22"/>
                  <p> Grant (O Lord) that by thy grace, I may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and chaſtiſe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of my fleſh, and all vicious affects therof, and that (with the gift of perſeuerance) I may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe my ſelfe in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall faſting, watching, praying, and other godly and ſpirituall Exerciſes. But chiefely grant (O Lord) that by the help of thy grace, I may be free from the ſinne of Gluttonie, and from all other deceits and ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of the Diuell. Let no temptation preuaile againſt mee, nor be able
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15678:23"/>to ſeparate me from thee. But rather grant that all theſe things may giue greater occaſion, that I may be the more firmely and ſtrongly vnited and ioyned vnto thee, and that I may with more heedfulnes, watch againſt all the ſubtile ſleights of the Tempter, to follow thy example in reſiſting, and to returne with thee in triumph.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15678:23"/>
                  <head>Ieſus ſuffereth diuers la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and neceſsities.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet leſu) that for the loue of mee, haſt beene afflicted in this world with infinite ſorrowes, and ſundry neceſſities, as heate, colde, hunger, thirſt, labour, and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with diuers watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, trauels, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all kinde of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations.</p>
                  <p>Grant (ô Lord) that for thy ſake, I may ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine all aduerſities with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15678:24"/>gladneſſe, as impoſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee, by the worke of thy hands, for the iuſt merit of my ſinnes. And that I may abide them with great patience.</p>
                  <p>Grant, that in all eſtates, as well in aduerſitie, as proſperitie; in griefe, as ioy; in troubles, as tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilities; I may ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer in thee, and neuer ſtart or ſwerue from thee, but that in all things, thy will may be my will: when thou ſtrikeſt, let mee not murmure againſt thee: when thou doſt afflict me with pouertie, and loſſe of worldly comforts, then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15678:24"/>lift vp my heart, that I may repoſe my wealth and my comfort in thee, ô bleſſed Sauiour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus prayeth and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O moſt ſweet IESVS) for that thou didſt performe many things for my ſake, whileſt thou didſt ſeeke the conuerſion and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of my Soule, and in no wiſe didſt omit the office, and dutie of a good Paſtor: but (euen as a true Shepheard, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15678:25"/>of the World) didſt watch in praying, and weary thy ſelfe in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling from Prouince to Prouince, and from place to place, to preach and teach, and publiſh thy heauenly doctrine.</p>
                  <p>I beſeech thee (O LORD) to impart this grace vnto mee, that at any time hereafter, I be neuer found ſlacke, or ſloathfull in thy ſeruice, but that I may be euer ready and forward to doe al good duties, reſpecting thy glory, and the good of my brethren, Grant, that I may feruently thirſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15678:25"/>after the ſauing health of all people, and that I may alwayes haue a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire &amp; zeale of thy name, and then ſhall I ſtand for the defence of Religion, and refuſe no labour or ſtudie, to promote thy glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is conuerſant amongſt men.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O benigne Ieſu) for that by conuerſing amongeſt men, thou wouldeſt cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully comfort them, and cure their infirmities, of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15678:26"/>thy great mercy.</p>
                  <p>Grant mee (O Lord) that I may haue a heart full of louing affections towards all men, that I may haue compaſſion on all that I perceiue to be in affliction. And grant me thy grace (O LORD) that I may eſteeme other mens miſeries as mine owne, that I may beare with other mens imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, with a ſincere heart, and without any paſſion of anger, hatred, or contempt; and that I may help and relieue their neceſſities after my abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, or at leaſt, haue a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15678:26"/>fellow-feeling and touch of their miſeries. O Lord, purge my ſoule perfectly from all vicious concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences and vaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, which haue any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in my heart, that the ſame (being hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of all theſe euils, and freed from all theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments) may ſafely flye vnto heauen, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reſt before it may be fit by pure loue and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to come vnto thy heauenly embracements.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:15678:27"/>
                  <head>Ieſus ſuffereth many things for vs.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O good Ieſu) that for the loue which thou beareſt vnto mee, thou diddeſt ſuffer innumerable iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, blaſphemies, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and perſecutions, and euen of thoſe chiefely, on whom thou beſtowedſt infinite benefits and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</p>
                  <p>I beſeech thee (O Lord) to giue me a pure, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and ſimple heart,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15678:27"/>that I may loue my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and that from my heart I may lament their euils and wickednes. That I may alwayes excuſe them if they treſpaſſe in any thing, and that (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending good for euill) I may truely imitate thy perfect charitie and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus commeth into Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O moſt louing IESVS) for that thou cameſt to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.5.</note>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:15678:28"/>humble and meeke, riding vpon an Aſſe-colt; and on them that came to meete thee, ſinging with pleaſant Hymnes, and glorious praiſes, thou ſheddedſt forth teares full of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which thy griefe did expreſſe, that was conceiued for the loſſe of ſo many ſoules, and the deſtruction of ſo beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a Citie.</p>
                  <p>Giue me (O Lord) an inward knowledge, and feeling of mine owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, that I may wholy humble my ſelfe, and openly acknowledge my
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15678:28"/>vileneſſe. That I may ſo far deſpiſe my ſelfe, that the flatterings, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and applauſes of men be not (hereafter) pleaſing vnto mee, but that I may daily mourne and bewaile, as well the ſinne of my neighbour, as the impietie of my ſelfe, ſtill reckoning and reputing his euill as mine owne,
<note place="margin">Ier. 9.1.</note> that mine head may be filled with the waters of bitter ſorrow, and mine eyes a fountain of teares, lamenting the deſtruction that thou haſt threatned againſt vnpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent perſons, becauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15678:29"/>they know not thoſe things which belong to their peace.
<note place="margin">Luk. 19.42</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="meditation">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:15678:29"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. III.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus waſheth the feete of his Diſciples.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Giue THEE thankes (O Lord Ieſu) for that thou (to preſcribe an end of the old Law) diddeſt eate the Paſcall Lambe in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem with thy Diſciples, and to giue an example to them of thy great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, &amp; ineffable loue, diddeſt waſh their feete, kneeling.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15678:30"/>
                  <p> I beſeech thee (O Lord) that this example may pierce my hart, and may ſuppreſſe all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and pride in mee. Giue me (O Lord) all humble ſubmiſſion, by which I may ſubiect my ſelfe to all men, not with conſtraint, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. Giue mee alſo perfect Obedience, by which I may fully ſatisfie thy Commandements, and the ruling power of them that command in thy Name. Stirre vp in me (O Lord) a moſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent Charitie, by which I may loue thee and my
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15678:30"/>neighbor with true pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſimplicitie. Let not the pride of my hart carry mee to diſdaine my brethren, but to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour my ſelfe to do them all chriſtian ſeruice, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in the refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their bodies, or miniſtring ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto their ſoules.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus ordayneth the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet Ieſu) that of thy moſt excellent Charitie, thou haſt ordayned the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15678:31"/>Sacrament of thy body and bloud,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26</note> and of thy vnſpeakable bountie haſt giuen thy ſelfe to be food for vs: and for that alſo thou haſt not refuſed to be here ſpiritually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with vs, to the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>O Lord, excite in me (I beſeech thee) a liuely deſire, and moſt ardent thirſt of this Sacrament. Grant, that I may come vnto this Table of life, receiue thee, by a liuely Faith, with chaſte Loue, with low Humilitie, with Puritie of heart, and with Sinceritie of mind. Grant
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15678:31"/>alſo, that my Soule may ſo thirſt after thee, and be ſo wounded with thy loue, that at the length, I may be admitted to poſſeſſe thy heauenly pleaſures, for the honour and glory of thy Name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus comforteth his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples at his laſt Supper.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet Ieſu) for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to leaue the world, thou diddeſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh and comfort thy Diſciples with words full of holy affection, and by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15678:32"/>earneſt prayer didſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to thy father,
<note place="margin">Iohn 17.9.11.</note> ſhewing thereby, with what loue thou diddeſt imbrace them, and all thoſe that ſhould beleeue in thee by their doctrine. I beſeech thee (O Lord) that my heart may feele a ſweetneſſe in thy words, and that they may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes more pleaſant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, then the honey or the honey-combe. O Lord, let the ſpirit of thy affection raigne in mee, that I may wholy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme my ſelfe into thy loue. Direct all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that in mee, and of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15678:32"/>me, alwayes thy will may be done.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus prayeth to his Father in the Garden.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O louing leſus) that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the Earth, (thy Armes ſpred forth) thou diddeſt pray vnto thy Father, commending thy ſelfe wholy into his hands, and praying that in all things not thy will but the will of thy Father might be fulfilled.
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.42</note> I beſeech thee (ô Lord) that in all tribulation, and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15678:33"/>I may runne vnto thee by heartie prayer, that I may belieue in thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence wholy, without election, or choiſe of my owne will, or the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any proper com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie.</p>
                  <p>Grant that I may not at any time ſhunne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities, nor be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from any good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe by the ſame. But that whatſoeuer ſhal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto mee, I may take it patiently, bearing and ſuffering all things with an humble &amp; quiet hart, as ſent vnto mee by thy holy hands. And that I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15678:33"/>may account them not as thy heauy iudgements, to confound me vtterly; but as thy chaſtiſements, to correct mee, and that not in thy fury, but in thy Fatherly loue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is apprehended.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (ô holy Ieſu) for that thou wouldeſt be taken with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men, and be bound by them as a wicked man and malifactor, and be brought before <hi>Annas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 26.47</note> and diddeſt not abhorre
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15678:34"/>to abide the Iudgement and ſentence againſt thee. Oh wonderfull meekneſſe of my Redeemer, whileſt thou wert apprehended, bound, ſcorn'd, and euill entreated, thou diddeſt neither lament, murmure nor grudge, but holding thy peace, didſt patiently follow them that did lead thee, draw thee, &amp; weary thee, thou diddeſt obey them that commanded thee, and with great pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience ſufferedſt the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which they infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vpon thee, when thou couldeſt haue had a legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Angels to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcued
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15678:34"/>thee, and haue cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the backes of thine enemies. O Lord, grant that ſuch an example of thy great vertue and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, may ſhine in mee, for the glory and honour of thy moſt holy Name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is ſmitten on the face.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (ô amiable Ieſu) that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before the proud &amp; ſtiffe-necked high-Prieſt, no otherwiſe, then if thou haddeſt beene a vile and abiect perſon,
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.64</note> thou wert ſtricken, and moſt pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15678:35"/>diddeſt ſuffer a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell blow, which one of his wicked miniſters ſtrucke on thy face. Oh Lord, I beſeech thee, mortifie in me all wrath and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; take from me all manner of enuy and hate, and extinguiſh in mee all deſires of reuenge, that when any one doth wrong and iniure me, I may not be troubled or moleſted, neither deuiſe at any time to be reuenged, but ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all things, with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for thy ſake, and by thy example, I may for thy loue, render to euery man good for euil. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="meditation">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:15678:35"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. IIII.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is diuerſly moleſted the night in which he is apprehended.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Giue THEE thankes (O ſweet IESVS) that in the night of thy Paſſion, thou wert ſcorned, and delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<note place="margin">Luke 22. &amp; Chap. 23.</note> ſmitten of thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and diuerſly iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and moleſted. Thou knoweſt (O LORD) how grieuous &amp; troubleſome it is to mee, to beare and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15678:36"/>ſuffer the leaſt wrong or iniurie. Thou knoweſt that my will and deſire is ſlow and ſlacke to all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and that all good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and appetites waxe cold in me. O Lord, for thy mercy, help my infirmitie: mortifie in mee all carnall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as heate of anger, hope of reuenge, and quicken thy graces with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mee.</p>
                  <p>Grant, that for no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, my minde be throwne downe, or deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Help me that I faint not vnder the burden of tribulations, which ſhall
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15678:36"/>fall vpon mee; neyther let me repine at the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done vnto mee by others; but giuing thee thankes for all things, I may referre all things to the honour and glory of thy Name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is accuſed before <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O Lord Ieſu) that ſtanding before <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 12.17</note> thou diddeſt not anſwere vnto the falſe complaints and accuſations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they did iniure thee,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15678:37"/>diddeſt paſſe ouer all things with ſilence, euen like a meek lambe, which openeth not his mouth, but is mute before the ſhearer.</p>
                  <p>Grant mee (ô Lord) that the reproches, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings, or reuilings of wicked men, make me not to ſwel againſt them, or puffe me vp with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, but that being taught by thy example, I may ouercome all them, when the caſe ſo requires, by ſilence and taciturnitie, that ſlander or impeach my good name. Giue me the grace of perfect Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15678:37"/>that I may ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſire that men praiſe me, nor be afraid to be diſpraiſed for thee: But to comfort mee with the reward of bleſſednes, that thou haſt aſſured them that are reuiled, and ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that theirs is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.10.11.12.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; quod eis magna est merces in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis;</hi> that great is their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in heauen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:15678:38"/>
                  <head>Ieſus brought before <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet IESVS) King of Heauen and Earth, that with great ſtirre and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the people, thou wert brought before <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 23.7.</note> by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Pilate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Giue mee fortitude (ô Lord) that perſecutions may not confound mee, nor the iniuries of my enemies prouoke mee to anger, nor that their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie make mee to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15678:38"/>bluſh, or be aſhamed, but that I may beare all things with meekneſſe &amp; patience, and ouer-come with ſilence, according to the preſcript of thy Commandements; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring alwaies whoſe cauſe I haue in hand, and that thou denyeſt them before thy Father, that deny thee before men. Strengthen me (ô Lord) in thy cauſe and quarrell, for thou art greater then the Princes of the earth, and canſt make thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to ſtand againſt them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:15678:39"/>
                  <head>Ieſus is accuſed before <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O holy IESVS) that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before <hi>Herod,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 23.9 10.</note> and accuſed before the chiefe Prieſts and Elders of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny crimes and iniquities, thou wouldeſt anſwere to nothing, but didſt iuſtifie thy cauſe by holding thy peace.</p>
                  <p>Giue mee the gift of ſilence (ô Lord) that I haue not at any time, a deſire to ſpeak vaine, idle, or vnclean ſpeeches, nor
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15678:39"/>that I waſte not my time in diſcourſing of barraine and vnfruitfull matters; but grant that my tongue vtter nothing that is not iuſt, honeſt, profitable, and conſonant to thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will. Let mee deteſt (ô Lord) the vice of backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, and that I be ſtill pleaſed to heare &amp; ſpeake well of all men: And when they ſhall band themſelues to plot my deſtruction, yet make me to pray for them; and in all things to be milde and mercifull,
<note place="margin">Luke 6.36</note> as my heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father is mercifull.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:15678:40"/>
                  <head>Ieſus is iudged more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked then <hi>Barrabas.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet Ieſu) that being compared with that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous murderer <hi>Barra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Marke 15.15. Act. 3.14.</note> thou wert iudged worſe, and more vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of life, then hee: ſo that homycide was ſet at libertie, and thou (the author of life) condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to dye. O King of eternall glory, what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter infamie could thy maieſtie be afflicted with? From hence (O LORD)
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15678:40"/>from hence it appeares, that thou art that liuely ſtone diſallowed of men, which God neuertheleſſe hath choſen to himſelfe, and placed in the head corner.</p>
                  <p>Grant (ô Lord) that I may preferre nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, that for any thing I be not changed from thee, but that I may account all things as vile and baſe that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto thee. Grant, that the poyſon of enuy neuer infect my minde, but that I may alwayes reſt in thee, and place my ſaluation in thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:15678:41"/>
                  <head>Ieſus is whipped.</head>
                  <p>IEſu, I giue thee thanks, that being ſpoyled of thy garments,
<note place="margin">Mar. 15.15</note> thou ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt, thy chaſte, holy, and naked fleſh to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon, and afterwards wouldeſt abide to be ſcourged, and whipped, that by thy wounds our wounds might be healed.</p>
                  <p>O Lord, deſpoyle my heart of all vncleane co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations: diſ-robe me of the old man with all his workes, and cloath mee with the new man, which
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15678:41"/>is created to thy image and ſimilitude, in Iuſtice and holineſſe, and grant that with all patience and humilitie, I may abide the ſcourge of thy father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſitation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is crowned with thornes.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O bountifull Ieſu) for that thou wert ſo diuerſly il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded after ſo great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies, ſo many wounds,
<note place="margin">Mar. 15.17</note> and after thy bloud ſo plentifully ſhed through thy whole body; &amp; to thy
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15678:42"/>greater reproach, they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred thee with a purple garment, &amp; put a crowne of thornes vpon thy head, with a Reed in thy hand, in ſtead of a Scepter, and bending their knees ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee as King (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mocked thee) ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Haile King of the Iewes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let (ô Lord) the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of this miſerable Tragedie be euer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in my heart, and neuer blotted out of my remembrance. Fixe thy charitie in my mind, that I may onely loue thee: thinke of thee, and of thy
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15678:42"/>iniuries; and ſo, euer reſt and depend on thee. That neyther tribulation, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, nor perſecutions, ſeparate mee from thee: neyther let it be grieuous vnto me at any time, if I be diſpiſed, contemned, mocked, and derided of men for thy ſake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus ſpeaketh to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O good Ieſu) that in this laborſome iourney, when thou wert brought forth
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15678:43"/>to be crucified, thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt louingly admoniſh the women that were la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting,
<note place="margin">Luk. 23.28</note> not to poure forth their plaints ouer thee, but ouer themſelues and their children.</p>
                  <p>Grant (ô Lord) that I may ſhed the teares of loue and compaſſion ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly, that the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my heart may be mollified, and made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in the ſight of thy Maieſtie. Grant (ô Lord) that being wholy inflamed with the loue of thee, I may little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing eſteeme of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſes, but that I may
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15678:43"/>imbrace thee, onely loue thee, and reſt in thee, world without end. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="meditation">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:15678:44"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. V.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus drinketh the Vineger mixt with gall.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Giue THEE thankes (O bountifull Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu) that thy bones being wearied,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.34</note> thy body being weakened, and thy ſelfe ouer-much preſſed with the weight of thy tortures &amp; ſorrowes, at length thou cameſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place of ſacrifice, where thou wert found wholy afflicted, &amp; almoſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15678:44"/>killed with thirſt; at which time thoſe barbarous and wicked Souldiers offered thee Vineger mixt with gall to drinke.</p>
                  <p>Let it pleaſe thee (ô Lord) that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of this Cup may extinguiſh in mee the inordinate concupiſcence of gluttonie, and delights of the fleſh; and grant, that at any time I giue not conſent to filthy and vnlawfull pleaſures, but giue mee the neceſſarie vertue of <hi>Temperance,</hi> that all other appetites and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights being ſuppreſſed, I may onely hunger and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15678:45"/>thirſt after thee, and place my whole pleaſures in thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Chriſt is crucified.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet IESVS) that wert cruelly diſtract and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: when they came to crucifie thee,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.35</note> did deſt alſo ſuffer that thy holy hands and feete ſhould be nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and faſtened to the Croſſe.</p>
                  <p>Graunt me (ô Lord) that with a faithfull and acceptable heart, I may alwayes be mindfull of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15678:45"/>that thy moſt ardent cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, by which thou wert moued ſo louingly to ſtretch forth thy armes, and open thy hands to be nailed, and to endure ſuch horrible torments.</p>
                  <p>Ariſe (O Lord) and wound my hart with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect charitie, and fill all my ſenſes with thy loue and affection, that at any time my deſires and cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be not ſeparated from thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:15678:46"/>
                  <head>Ieſus hangeth vpon the Croſſe.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O moſt holy Jeſu) that for three houres ſpace thou diddeſt hang vpon the Croſſe,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.18</note> moleſted with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and intollerable infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, abundantly ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thy bloud, and in all thy members ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning immeaſurahle for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. Faſten (O Lord) my wretched Soule (which lyeth proſtrate on the ground) to the ſame Croſſe: purge the ſame
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15678:46"/>from vncleanneſſe of Sin, and filthy deſires, waſhing it with the flowing ſprings of thy precious bloud, which yeeldeth life and ſaluation. Refuſe not (ô Lord) to cleanſe me with the ſame bloud, to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie and make me pure with that moſt precious liquour of life. Offer the ſame (ô Lord) vnto thy Father in remedie and full ſatisfaction of my ſinnes and iniquities. Grant (O Lord) I befeech thee, that my heart may taſte, and my ſoule may drinke of the ſweet drops of that thy precious bloud.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:15678:47"/>
                  <head>Ieſus hangeth betweene two Theeues.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O ſweet Ieſu) that for the loue of me thou wouldeſt be hanged betweene two Theeues,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.38</note> and be alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted like vnto them, that by this thy meruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous humilitie, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, thou mighteſt heale and vtterly deſtroy our haughtie pride and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</p>
                  <p>Grant (ô Lord) ſo to exalt my ſpirit, that I may deſpiſe all the things of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15678:47"/>this world, and that I may onely behold thee, onely loue thee, that I may neuer meditate of any thing, but that thou (ô LORD) and thy ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings may be freſh blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in my heart; that I may onely thinke of thee, onely talke of thee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light my ſelfe in thee, and that all my actions be in thee, and by thee, and that nothing may ſatisfie my minde without thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:15678:48"/>
                  <head>Ieſus prayeth for them that crucifie him.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O beloued Ieſus) that wert ſo good to them that handled thee in ſuch hard meaſure, and didſt alſo pray vnto thy Father for them that crucified thee,
<note place="margin">Luk. 23.34</note> ſaying; <hi>Forgiue them (Father) for they know not what they doe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Giue mee grace (O Lord) that I may haue true patience and meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; by which being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (according to the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15678:48"/>example which thou haſt giuen mee, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement which thou haſt left mee) I may loue my enemies, &amp; doe good to them that hate mee, and that I may pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for them, that thou forgiue all their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is ſcoffed on the Croſſe.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O bountifull IESV) that wert ſcorned &amp; deſpiſed of thine enemies,
<note place="margin">Luk. 23.36</note> &amp; ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt ſo many iniuries and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15678:49"/>blaſphemies, euen at that time, in which they infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſuch ineffable griefes &amp; ſorrowes on the croſſe vpon thy naked body.</p>
                  <p>Grant mee grace, (O Lord) that being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the humilitie which thou didſt ſuffer, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience with which thou didſt abide ſo great do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and infamies, I may alſo with the like ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance endure all aduerfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, perſeuering with thee (euen vnto death) in the croſſe of patience. Let no force of temptation, no tempeſt of tribulation, nor no affliction of iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15678:49"/>with-draw mee from any good purpoſe begun. Let neither life nor death, things preſent, nor things to come, nor any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeparate mee from thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus promiſeth Paradiſe to one of the Theeues.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O excellent IESV) that didſt alſo ſuffer the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and blaſphemies of one of the Theeues,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.38</note> and to the other that confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſinnes vnto thee, and ſet forth thy inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15678:50"/>with a pure Faith, didſt promiſe the glory of Paradiſe.</p>
                  <p>Oh happy mee, if I might euer become ſo bleſſed, as to be ſo reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the eyes of thy mercie, with which thou didſt behold that happy Theefe; and to liue ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently, by the help of thy grace, that at the end of my life, I may heare this thy moſt ſweet ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with mee in Paradiſe!</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="meditation">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:15678:50"/>
               <head>MEDITAT. VI.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus complaineth that hee is forſaken of his Father.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Giue THEE thanks (ô moſt ſweet Ieſu) that thy Wounds being opened, thy head crowned with thornes, thy hands and feete fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Croſſe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.46</note> thou didſt ſay; <hi>Oh God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Worke in me (ô Lord) that in all aduerſities and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15678:51"/>temptations, I may flye vnto thee my louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and (diſtruſting in my ſelfe) may onely truſt in thee, and wholy reſigne my ſelfe into thy hands.</p>
                  <p>Grant (O Lord) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, to wound the inward parts of my Soule, with the remembrance of thy wounds. Let them be imprinted in the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of my heart, and ſo let mee be ſatisfied with thee, that I may thinke of none but thee, nor ſeeke any other then thee, that ſeeking, I may finde thee; and found, I may poſſeſſe thee for euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:15678:51"/>
                  <head>Ieſus thirſteth vpon the Croſſe.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O Lord Ieſus Chriſt) that hauing thy body weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and drie, by reaſon of thy moſt grieuous torments, and great effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy bloud, diddeſt vehemently thirſt,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.28</note> and burning with deſire of our ſaluation, didſt ſay, <hi>I thirſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Grant (O Lord) that I may ardently thirſt after thy honour, and the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of Soules. Let me
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15678:52"/>wholy occupy my ſelfe in the ſame, &amp; conforme my ſelfe to thy holy will, doing as much as my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate is able. I beſeech thee, that no loue of tranſitory things carry me away, nor no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture draw mee into pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous dangers. Nay, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let mee embrace all things for the loue of thee, that are to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, but let mee ſtill hold thee more deare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee then any thing, and onely in thee finde reſt and quietneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:15678:52"/>
                  <head>Ieſus drinketh gall vpon the Croſſe.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O moſt mercifull IESVS) that in the houre of thy death;
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.34</note> to quench thy thirſt, thou wouldeſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a Sponge full of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vnto thy mouth, that by taſting in that thy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted eſtate, thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſatisfie thy heauenly Father for all our intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perances and voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and leaue vnto vs a miraculous example of thy pouertie.</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:15678:53"/>
                  <p> Grant mee grace (O Lord) that for the loue of thee, I may deſpiſe all dilicious ſauours, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite banquets, and that I may be contented with modeſtie and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, to eate &amp; drinke that onely that may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the ſuſtenance of this body, rendring thee infinite thankes for the ſame. Purifie and heale my Soule, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is acceptable vnto thee, may be pleaſing to mee; and what diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee, may be vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery and loathſome vnto mee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:15678:53"/>
                  <head>Ieſus endeth the worke of our Redemption.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O Ieſu, the feruent louer of mankinde) that in ſo abſolute order thou didſt end the worke of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, offering thy ſelfe a liuely Sacrifice on the Altar of the Croſſe for the ſins of the world.</p>
                  <p>I beſeech thee (O my Redeemer) that thou wouldeſt vouchſafe to be the onely harbour of my heart, and the ſcope of my cogitations, wordes,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:15678:54"/>and workes, that in all things with pure &amp; chaſte intention, I may onely looke on thee, that I doe that thing onely which thy glorie requireth, that nothing pleaſe mee, but thee; and that I deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſides thee. Grant (ô Lord) that hereafter at any time, I be not ſlacke or remiſſe in thy ſeruice, but that (the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of thy holy Spirit being daily renued in mee) my diligence may increaſe more and more in thy praiſe and ſeruice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:15678:54"/>
                  <head>Ieſus dyeth.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O moſt meeke Ieſus) that thou diddeſt call Death, and command thy Spirit to leaue the priſon of the fleſh (being commended into the hands of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) in which thing thou declareſt,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.30</note> that thou art that true Shepheard, that dyed for the ſafeguard of his flocke.</p>
                  <p>Grant mee (O Lord) that being dead to ſinne, and all wicked vices, I may onely liue vnto thee,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15678:55"/>that (the courſe of this life being ended in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) I may forth-with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into thee, that art the true Paradiſe of our ſoules.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ieſus is buried.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O beloued Ieſus) that with great complaints and mournings of thy friends thou wert taken from the Croſſe,
<note place="margin">Iohn 19.40.41.</note> annointed with moſt precious ointments, wrapped in linnen cloths, &amp; put into another mans Sepulchre: O Lord, bury
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15678:55"/>with thee all my ſenſes, and deſires, that being ioyned to thee in the ſtrong linckes of loue, I may be, as it were, dead, in thoſe things that diſpleaſe thee. And of the contrary part, in all things that pleaſe thee, let mee be wholy aliue, ready, and ioyfull; let me onely be delighted in thee, my Redeemer and treaſure of my Soule. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="meditation">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:15678:56"/>
               <head>MED<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> haſt not ſpared to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the torments of death and hell for my ſake, that thou mighteſt aduance mee into thy Kingdome. Let the conſideration of this (ô God) terrifie me from ſinne, becauſe thou ſparedſt not thine onely begotten Sonne, but that
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15678:56"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> endure the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Let it alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> in my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that thogh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of wrath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> in mee,
<note place="margin">Iob 6.4.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> thereof drinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſpirit, yet I may ſtill remember, that thou my Sauiour haſt ſatisfied for all my ſins, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered both Death and Hell,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.15</note> when thou diddeſt leade captiuitie captiue: and by the ſpoyle of all principalities &amp; powers of darkneſſe, haſt ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them vp into victory. Behold, (O Lord) behold
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15678:57"/>my infirmities, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that I am in thy hands but as the clay in the hands of the Potter: If thou try me, giue mee patience to beare it, and when thou ſmiteſt me, lift me vp againe; and if thy terrours ſhould fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee,
<note place="margin">Iob. 6.4.</note> yet teach me (ô Lord) to reſolue that it is thy fatherly worke to kill ſinne in me, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mortified in my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh, may be raiſed vp vnto the life of glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:15678:57"/>
                  <head>Christ is riſen from the dead.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O good IESVS) that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriouſly comming out of thy Sepulchre with moſt noble triumph, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou haddeſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come death, diddeſt riſe againe the third day in great Glory and Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, viſiting thy Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples &amp; comforting them with exceeding gladnes.</p>
                  <p>Grant (ô Lord) that being quickned from death, and the deadly
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15678:58"/>action of my ſinfull life, and vngodly conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I may walke in the newneſſe of life, and ſeeke onely for thoſe things which are high and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, and not thoſe things which are vile and tranſitorie, that when thou (being the true life) ſhalt ſecondly appeare in the glory of thy Father with the Angels, I may likewiſe appeare with thee in glory, and be made euerlaſtingly bleſſed in the ioyfull fruition of that Kingdome that neuer ſhall haue end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:15678:58"/>
                  <head>Ieſus aſcendeth into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O louing Ieſus) that fortie dayes being ouer-paſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy Reſurrection, thy Diſciples did behold thee triumphantly,
<note place="margin">Acts 1.</note> and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly aſcending into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where ſitting at the right hand of thy Father, thou ruleſt, and raigneſt as King, world without end.</p>
                  <p>Let it be pleaſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy goodneſſe (ô Lord) that my Soule may be
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15678:59"/>rauiſhed with the loue of thee,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.1</note> and to ſeeke thoſe things that are aboue, and may deſpiſe al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things: Let it alwayes aſpire vnto thee, that it may be lift vp vnto the heauens, from whence muſt come my comfort, my crowne, and my ioy. And that my prayer may aſcend vnto thee as the morning Incenſe, let it affect, or be delighted in nothing, but in thee my onely Lord and God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:15678:59"/>
                  <head>Ieſus ſendeth the <hi>HOLY GHOST.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O moſt louing Ieſus) that didſt ſend thy holy ſpirit vpon thy elect which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuered in prayer, and didſt ſend them to preach and teach the people throughout all the world.</p>
                  <p>I beſeech thee (O LORD) to purifie the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts of my heart, and to giue mee true pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and cleannes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that the ſame Comforter finding in my
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15678:60"/>ſoule an acceptable dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-place, may adorne and beautifie it with the moſt fruitfull gifts of his Graces. Let him onely comfort me, onely ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then me, onely rule mee, and be onely reſpected of me. Let me neuer want the comfort of thy Spirit (ô God) but that I may finde him in his ſweet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of grace and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, to ſanctifie my Soule, and to ſtrengthen the inward man in all godlineſſe and vertue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:15678:60"/>
                  <head>Ieſus ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead.</head>
                  <p>I Giue thee thankes (O bountifull IESVS) that when thou ſhalt come at that laſt day to iudge the world, thou wilt render to euery one according to his workes, eyther the ioy of eternal life, or euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Grant (ô my louing Father) that I may haue grace to ſpend the courſe of my life in innocencie, according to thy holy will, that at length, my
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:15678:61"/>Soule leauing the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment of the body, may be preſented blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe before thee, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing garniſhed with many vertues, may through thy mercy be receiued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Tabernacle of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that it may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie and praiſe thee in the fellowſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Saints, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:15678:61"/>
            <head>A PRAYER, or Meditation on <hi>the Name of</hi> IESVS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Good IESV, ô ſweet Ieſu, the Sonne of the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> full of pittie and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; ô ſweet Ieſu, after thine infinite goodneſſe, haue mercy vpon mee; ô bountifull Ieſu through that thy precious bloud, which thou didſt plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhed vpon the Altar
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15678:62"/>of the Croſſe for wicked Sinners, that thou waſh mee from all my ſinnes and iniquities, and that thou deſpiſe not thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, which humbly prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and calleth vpon thee by this holy Name Ieſus.</p>
            <p>This Name Ieſus is a ſweet Name; yea, it is ſweeter then any Nectar &amp; Ambroſia. This Name of Ieſus bringeth life and ſaluation: for what is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus but a Sauiour?</p>
            <p>Therfore ô good Ieſus, which of thy goodneſſe haſt created me, and by thy precious bloud haſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:15678:62"/>redeemed mee; ſuffer not my Soule to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinnes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>O good IESVS, let not mine iniquities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne my Soule, which thou haſt made of thine infinite goodneſſe: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in me (ô good Ieſu) that which is thine, and take from me all my ſinfull and filthy enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</p>
            <p>O good Ieſu, haue mercy vpon mee ſo long as I am in this world, leaſt at that terrible day of Iudgement I be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15678:63"/>with the wicked and reprobate.</p>
            <p>O good Ieſus, if ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy Iuſtice, I (being a peruerſe ſinner) deſerue to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by reaſon of my grieuous ſinnes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, I humbly appeale from thy ſeuere Iuſtice, to thy mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, truſting altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (ô my Lord Ieſus) that thou wilt be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto mee, and wilt haue mercy on my ſoule, as a louing and pittifull Father. What profit will be to thee (O good IESVS) in my fleſh, if
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15678:63"/>my Soule deſcend into hell? for it is certaine that in hell none ſhall confeſſe the holy Name of Ieſus.</p>
            <p>O moſt merciful Ieſus haue mercy on vs, ô moſt ſweet Ieſus, deliuer vs from all our tribulations, and aduerſities; ô excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Ieſus be good vnto vs miſerable ſinners; ô moſt holy IESVS, grant that our ſoules may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the fellowſhip of the Elect in thy heauenly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation. Strengthen mee ô moſt louing Ieſus, with the ſauing health of all that truſt in thee. O Ieſu the Son of the moſt holy
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:15678:64"/>Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> giue vnto vs thy Mercy, Grace, Wiſedome, Charitie, Chaſtitie, Humilitie, and Patience in all our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, that wee may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes praiſe and glorifie thee, our Lord IESVS, which liueſt and raigneſt God world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:15678:64"/>
            <head>A ſhort Prayer for Morning.</head>
            <p>I Thanke thee, moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, my maker and preſeruer, that thou haſt ſo louingly vouchſafed to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my ſafetie this night paſt, giuing me ſweet ſleepe, to the refreſhment of my ſoule and weake body. So (of thy goodneſſe) vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to extend thy louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour towards me this day, that thereby I may be both ſafely preſerued from all kinde of euill, and imploy my ſelfe diligently vnto the execution of my vocation, to thy glory, and to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of me &amp; mine, through Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:15678:65"/>
            <head>A ſhort Prayer for Euening.</head>
            <p>O Almightie Lord God, I thanke thee, that this day paſt, thou haſt of thy mercy vouchſafed vnto me thy poore creature, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly protection againſt all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and euils, but alſo all things neceſſarie. I humbly beſeech thee, of that ſame thy mercy, and for thy Son Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the like protection and fauor toward me this night, that I may enioy at thine hands ſafe and quiet reſt, to the comfort and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of my body and ſoule, for Ieſus Chriſts ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15678:65"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
